All right, static site generators, everybody's talking about them.
Seems like a new one pops up every day.
Right. And this time we're doing a deep dive on HydePHP.
At least that's what their docs are calling it.
Catchy name.
It really is. And they're making some bold claims.
Elegance and power. All in one package.
Yeah, that focused on writing content, not markup line, caught my eye.
Right. Because who wants to mess around with HTML tags all day?
Not me.
Speak for yourself. I kind of like them.
Yeah, but I see their point.
They mentioned using Markdown, which is great for, well,
you know, just writing and Laravel, which is a PHP framework, right?
Kind of seems like overkill for a static site.
Well, they're actually using Laravel zero.
It's a stripped down version of Laravel built for speed.
So they get the structure of a framework without all the plot.
Ah, so it's like they optimized it specifically for static sites?
Exactly. They're playing to the strength of static sites, which is smart.
And speaking of strengths, they really hype up the whole blazing fast angle.
But is speed really that big of a deal?
Absolutely. First off, user experience, slow site,
say goodbye to visitors.
Ouch. Yeah, nobody's got time for that spinny wheel of doom.
Exactly. But it's also about the developer experience.
If building and rebuilding the site is super fast, like they claim,
it makes the developer's life way easier.
Quicker iterations, faster theme back loops, you know the drill.
Makes sense. It's like the faster you can see your changes,
the faster you can get stuff done.
They also talk about being simple to get started, but powerful when you need it.
Right. Like that classic balancing act.
Exactly. But who are they targeting with that message?
Who's the ideal HydePHP user?
Well, they definitely assume some command line comfort.
You got to be okay, get in your hands a little dirty with code.
So not exactly aimed at your average WordPress blogger, though?
Probably not.
But they do emphasize no endless configuration,
which suggests a streamlined experience.
Might appeal to folks familiar with Jekyll or other minimal setups.
So previous static set experiences a plus. Got it.
And they even include Tailwind CSS by default.
Smart move. Tailwind's super popular for a reason.
For those who haven't used it, what's the big deal with Tailwind?
It's a utility for CSS framework.
Basically pre-built styles, you can apply directly to your HTML,
make styling super fast.
Ah, so it's like building blocks for your website's design.
Exactly. And by including it by default,
they're not going out a setup step right off the bat.
Plus, Tailwind's known for producing clean,
professional looking sites.
So it aligns with that elegant thing they're going for.
Okay, you've convinced me, I'm ready to give it a shot.
But real talk, how is time when we're talking to get this thing up and run it?
Not bad at all, actually.
You need PHP 8.1 or higher, pretty standard stuff.
Check.
And Composer, it's a package manager for PHP.
Helps you wrangle all the dependencies.
Right, kind of like, what's it called?
NPM for JavaScript?
Yeah, kind of like that.
Yeah.
And installations of Breeze just follow the instructions on the HydePHP website.
No crazy workarounds or anything?
Nope, they keep it nice and straight forward.
Use it to my ears.
Okay, so I've got it installed.
I'm ready to roll what's the workflow actually like.
Almost too easy.
You basically just drop your Markdown files into a specific folder
or use hyde commands to generate some starter templates.
Then you run hyde build and bam,
you've got a directory full of static HTML ready to deploy wherever you want.
Hold on, did you just say drop Markdown files and go?
That's it?
Pretty much.
It's surprisingly streamlined.
I got to ask what's the catch.
Well, the big question is customization.
They talk a big game about ease of use,
but how far does that go?
Can you really get under the hood and tweak things?
Or do you hit a point where you need to break out the full Laravel toolkit?
Yeah, that's something to consider.
Yeah.
Like is it truly flexible or more of a
works great if you stay within the lines kind of thing?
Exactly.
That's something you'd want to investigate further.
Especially if you're planning on building something really custom.
But for simpler sites or getting up and running quickly,
HydePHP looks pretty darn slick.
It really does.
So to sum it all up, HydePHP.
It's like that shiny new sports car in the showroom.
Potentially powerful promises a smooth ride,
but maybe take it for a test drive before you sign on the dotted line.
That being said, that test drive might just inspire your next awesome website.
This has been the Deep Dive.